My name is Victory Imasuen.
I am a deportee from Libya; me and my colleague.
I am from Edo State, Nigeria.
I'm here to share the experience I had in Libya
and I want to give testimony about what God has done in my life.
Before I went to Libya, it was very difficult for me to start up something as a young boy.
When I lost my father at the age of 11, it was only my mother and I
who could take care of six children.
During that time, it was not easy for me and my mother.
I had to take the step of faith to see if there was anything that I could do to assist my mother.
So, I did all sorts of jobs and activities to sponsor myself in school.
After all, I found myself learning how to cut hair.
Few months later, I became very good at it and I worked as a professional barber.
One day, I was cutting one of my customers' hair and he advised me saying that
since I know how to cut very well, if I could go to Europe, I would make it
and earn a lot of money to take care of my juniors and I would be able to do what I wanted to do.
I asked him how much it would cost me and he said it was 350,000 Naira.
I said that I didn't have such a big money and he asked how much I had.
I said I only had 140,000 Naira which was the money that I had been contributing
at the end of every month – 10,000 Naira – and that was only I could save out of my salary.
The man then said that he would help me; if I paid with what I had
and when I got to Europe, I could pay the remaining money.
Then I gave him 140,000 Naira.
We moved from Benin to Kano and from there to Agadez.
We took a car to the desert.
On the third day, we were moving in convoy with different passengers
who were also going to Europe and it was about 30 cars.
One of the cars had a terrible accident which only two or three passengers were able to survive.
Then on the fourth day, our water got finished and that was when everything started.
There was no more water for us to drink and I almost gave up on myself
but something was telling me that if I gave up on that point, who would take care of my juniors
who were the reason I started the journey.
It was as if a force came upon me; I had strength and I was no more thirsty.
On the sixth day, we arrived in Libya.
When we got there, the driver said that the trafficker did not pay for our transportation.
We said that we had already paid our money to him.
We tried to make a call but to no avail.
The man said that he was going to sell us into slavery.
The driver took us to Sabat to sell us into slavery and there were ladies among us.
We were 11 in number.
When we got there, we were sold to a Ghanaian man and he took us to his place.
In his place, there was another underground house in which whenever they beat us
but even though we shouted, nobody would hear and come to help us.
When I entered, I met a lot of Nigerians and people from other countries.
We were locked up in a small room and we were about over 200 people.
There were also ladies locked up in a room opposite ours.
The next day, they started beating me saying that I should call my mother to send me money.
That was the time my mother got to know that I was not in Nigeria because I did not tell her before I left.
Then she knew that I was not in Nigeria and she asked me where I was.
I told her that I was in Libya and I explained the situation I was in.
I told her of the money that they were demanding – 250,000 Naira.
She said, "I don’t have such a big money. How am I going to get the money?"
For months, I did not hear from my mother; not even a phone call.
When there was no call for me, they kept on beating me everyday.
Even going to the toilet was very difficult at times.
When I went to use the toilet, it was very painful and discharged blood at that point.
For the ladies, they would wait three or five days for their money but if the money did not come,
they would sell the ladies to do prostitution.
Some women would come to our place to buy the ladies and take them to traffickers
where they would start prostitution.
Even though she got to the point where she would be able to pay the money back,
the traffickers would sell them to another trafficker so that she could start another work.
I saw such case more than three times.
On the eighth month, I got freedom back; I paid money and came out of the prison.
To get to feed myself was very difficult because when I called my mother,
she said she did not have money for feeding.
I had to go wherever they sent us to work.
A lot of ladies became pregnant without knowing the father of the babies
because they would sleep with men from different countries.
Due to the prostitution, most of them became pregnant without knowing the father of the child.
I was working trying to make money to feed myself.
About two months later, after I came out of the prison, I was able to raise some money
by working in a barber shop.
Then, I planned to move to Tripoli to cross the border but before I could get there, I was kidnapped again.
They said they would deport us back to Nigeria.
When we got there, they took us to a prison and I met a lot of Nigerians there; more than 10,000.
The life was very difficult in the prison.
Even the way we ate – we ate only once in a day; one piece of bread and nothing else.
Even the water we drank was salt water.
They decided to deport ladies first and at that point, we asked the ladies
that whenever they left, they should try to take some men claiming to be their husbands.
Luckily, one of the ladies took me and claimed that I was her husband.
That was how I found myself in Tripoli deportee camp before a CNN reporter came.
I said to myself that I might get some help from this media if I spoke, so I decided to speak
to CNN and they interviewed me.
We see on the screens of TVs...
We have just heard from the brother, who was sharing his experience during his stay in Libya.
He said that he had left Nigeria as a professional barber.
After arriving to Libya he went through lot of experiences.
He ended up in the underground house.
Many of people there were packed in small cells, which were designed for two persons.
He was sold to kidnappers who told him that he had to pay the ransom, in order to get his freedom.
He said it had been by chance that somebody was able to rescue him out, paying the kidnappers the ransom.
After leaving this place he ended up in a prison.
From the prison he was sent to the deportation camp.
While his stay in the deportation camp, the CNN came to make a report on deportees there.
We just want to ask our brothers...
On the screen of TV we see our brother.
Can you just explain what were you doing there?
On the programme of the TV, I am the one who was talking.
When CNN came, I decided to speak because I really needed help.
At the end, nothing came out of it and finally, I was deported to Nigeria
through IOM (International Organisation for Migration) who assists deportees from Libya.
I decided to come to The SCOAN
because even before I left, I heard that The SCOAN renders help to others and also deportees like me.
I decided to come here to seek prayers because I thought it was because of the curse
which made it really hard on me and I prayed every curse and poverty in my family would break.
I would share my testimony of how God brought me back alive.
I really want to say, "Thank You, Lord" for everything He has done for me.
We just heard from the brother -
after he was taken to the deportation camp, the CNN came to interview them about their experiences
of their journey through Libya.
He was able to share his experience.
He was deported back to Nigeria - he was taken to his State
but he decided to come to Lagos, to The SCOAN, because he knew God would surely use T.B. Joshua
and Emmanuel TV partners to rescue him out of this terrible conditions,
that he had found himself in, during his journey by illegal means in Libya.
That is why he is here today to seek help from the man of God, Prophet T.B. Joshua and Emmanuel TV partners
so that he can start his life anew.
Praise the Lord.
I'm Osazee Aghimiee.
I'm from Edo State.
I was a driver before I left Nigeria.
I have married and have one baby boy who was born just three days before I left Nigeria.
Suddenly, most of my friends called me and told me that I should come to Europe.
I agreed with them and told them that I would gather money.
As a driver, I would follow my friends to Lagos, Abuja or Port Harcourt, any time I didn't have work.
From there, I gathered a little money.
One day, I told my wife that I wanted to travel to Libya
and she said that I should manage with little work I had.
When the day came, I woke up and she was wearing a baby belt holding our baby.
I left the house with my passport and everything I needed.
I paid 200,000 Naira to the trafficker who said he would take me to Libya.
That day, I ran away to his house and on the third day, we left for Libya.
When we got to Agadez, they put us inside 24 vehicles.
They arranged us into 24 cars.
There were 34 people in each vehicle.
We left for Sahara desert.
After two days, close to Duruku, one of the cars had an accident.
We came down to help them and buried four people who died.
The car was going fast.
Our driver said that we would not bury them because he was in hurry.
Where actually was your destination?
My destination was Europe.
When I arrived in Saba, I called my wife that I was already in Libya.
I asked her to help me to send money for my account so that I could use it to cross the border.
But, she refused because she just gave birth to my baby so she needed to take care of him.
I said that there was no problem because I would be working.
I saved 1,500 Dinars and they took me to the seaside.
When we got to the seaside, they put us in lapalapa (balloon boat).
The same night, they pushed us.
From Tunis to Malta then to International sea where there was a boundary.
Getting to international sea, we saw a very big ship surrounded by almost 25 balloon boats.
Before we knew it, we saw foreign ladies coming and they told us that
they were international rescuers and they came to rescue us.
They welcomed and addressed us that we should wait
then they would come back in 20 minutes to rescue us.
There were also other boats to the ship and they couldn't attend to all of us
so we should wait and we were waiting for them.
Within a short time, the Libyan terrorists called 'Asma boys' drove speed boats to the big ship.
They started entering balloon boats; one of them entered my boat and others to other boats.
They drove our balloon boats away and said they were taking us back to Libya.
As they drove our boats, everybody was shouting for help.
The three ladies came and begged them to leave us because we were already on international sea.
They refused and started using guns to hit people inside the boats.
They drove us to Janzur and Tripoli.
As we were going, the Asma boys poured the fuel we kept for our journey inside the boat.
There was already water in the balloon boat.
They poured the fuel inside the balloon boat.
The sea water is with salt - you cannot mix this water with fuel.
After they poured the fuel inside the boat, they told us to lie down and we did.
Then the fuel started burning us; if you see my leg, you can see the scar.
The second time, after I was freed from them, the man who was holding the camp came
and said that the second chance had come and they wanted to try to push us again.
We said as long as we decided to go to Europe, there was no problem.
At night, we took out the balloon boats that we kept in the camp
and they took us to the seaside; we were 160 people.
They took us to the seaside and pumped and fixed the boats.
When we drove about five hours on the Mediterranean sea, we saw a fisherman
and he said we should go back because the wave would become stronger within an hour
and we still had to travel more than three hours.
We told our captain to turn the boat but he said we couldn’t lose the second chance.
As we continued, people were shouting; because the fisherman warned us to go back,
they were shouting and started leaving the boat so, we told the captain to turn the boat.
Before we realised, the weather changed and started rocking the boats.
A lot of people died; we were 160 in number.
I can remember that it was about 20 people survived.
Two girls from my village died.
Almost 100 people had died during that journey.
I was praying to God to take me to Heaven and let me see my baby.
Suddenly, a bird came dipped into the water, sprinkling the water around.
As the sea became calm, 10 minutes later, we saw a big ship coming from Libya.
They came to rescue us and asked whether we were still going to Italy.
We said we're going back to prison and they took us to deportation camp in Subratha to Gharyan.
When we got to Gharyan, we saw many people – Nigerians, Gambians.
In the deportation camp in Gharyan, people from IOM used to come to check if we were doing fine.
We would say that we were fine because if we didn't, when the IOM left, they would beat us.
After this experience, every time IOM came to ask us, we always had to say we were fine.
They then transferred us from Gharyan to Tajoura.
As we got to Tajoura, they told us that a Nigerian ambassador has come to register us
and give us tickets to flight to Nigeria.
We spent three months before IOM came and shared T-shirts and gave us necessaries.
We were finally deported to Nigeria and that was this week.
When we came back, they said we should go back to our states but I said that I didn't want to
but I wanted to go to The SCOAN and meet the man of God, T.B. Joshua who I had heard about.
I came to The SCOAN with my friends and as we came, they gave us food and water
and they gave us 1.2 million Naira to share with my friends.
On behalf of Prophet T.B. Joshua and Emmanuel TV partners - they want to support you, deportees.
They want to support you with a sum of 1.2 million Naira.
Deportees Receive 1.2 Million Naira
From T.B. Joshua & Emmanuel TV Partners
Everybody in this country, Nigeria, please note that it is not safe to travel by land.
Just wait for God's time and it would be the best.
If you are a tailor or whatever profession you are, just be satisfied with what you have.
Ask God to help you.
Thank you.
I want to advise young people to try to be yourself and wait for God's time because God's time is the best.
If I knew, I wouldn't have joined the journey.
I also learnt my lesson.
We have heard from the brothers, who have been able to share with us their experiences
from their journey to Libya.
They are not the first set of deportees.
For months, we have been receiving thousands and thousands of deportees from Libya.
As they said, after their landing here they made the decision to come to The SCOAN, having heard of
the goodness of the God Almighty through His anointed, Prophet T.B. Joshua and Emmanuel TV partners
in the lives of other deportees.
They said that was why they also made this decision to come down to The SCOAN.
They are here today sharing their experience.
When they and thousands of other deportees came to The SCOAN, they were welcomed and given money.
They have come here to share the experience to the world and give advice that
if you want embark on any journey abroad, it must be taken legally.
We have heard their experience.
They have made their heart desires known to Prophet of God - T.B. Joshua.
They are here today to receive help from man of God -T.B. Joshua and Emmanuel TV partners,
so that they can be useful to the society and avoid falling into bad companion.
They have shared their experiences during the Sunday service.
The man of God has made us understand that we are called to respond to all humans in need -
that is what love entails.
We cannot look the other way when our brothers and sisters are in need.
Jesus Christ has given us that commission to respond to needs of others.
That is exactly what the man of God, Prophet T.B. Joshua and Emmanuel TV partners do.
In addition to the money already given, the man of God wants to give each of these two brothers
the sum of 200.000 Naira.
The purpose of this is to establish them out there.
They have spent their all savings to go Libya, where they were able to gain nothing -
they have come back empty-handed.
In order to prevent them from entering the bad companion in the world Prophet T.B. Joshua
and Emmanuel TV partners help them financially, apart from the money given them initially.
They also received a book titled "the Mirror" - a faith building book.
As you read it your faith will be lifted up - you will see a need to follow Jesus Christ along the way.
We give glory to God Almighty for what He has used the man of God, Prophet T.B. Joshua to do in the lives
of these two brothers and other people who had been deported from Libya.
I want to say thank you to Prophet T.B. Joshua for helping me with the sum of 200.000 Naira.
With this, I will be able to start something.
I interviewed with several media who targeted us from other countries but nothing returned.
But with this...
I don’t know how to express myself but I really want to say thank you
for everything that you have done for me and my fellow members who are also deportees.
May God continue to bless you and grant you for many years ahead.
Thank you for everything you have done for us, sir.
May God bless you, sir.
I thank God for my life and Prophet T.B. Joshua and Emmanuel TV partners
for giving me the sum of 200,000 Naira to start up my life.
Thank you.
We have heard the testimony from the brother of what God Almighty has done in his life,
using the Prophet T.B. Joshua and Emmanuel TV partners.
We also give glory to God Almighty for what He has done in your lives.
We want to advise you that you make sure to follow God along the way,
making His Word a standard for your life - and the Lord will continue to be with you, in Jesus' name.
Thank you very much.